Finding Aid for the Medical Artifacts Collection
Eskind Biomedical Library Manuscripts Collection
- Box 85 860 Medicine Case. Dark brown leather ca. 1880 containing an assortment of nineteen various medicine bottles. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 861 Pelvimeter, ca. 1930, steel, chrome-plated, centimeter graduated scale etched on side. Manufactured by the Betz Company. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 862 Vaginal retractor, solid metal, ca. 20th century. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 863 Vaginal retractor, solid metal, ca. 20th century. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 864 Vaginal retractor, solid metal with wooden handle, ca. 1875. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 865 Nasal specula (three), ca. 1920, metal, two manufactured by Dittmar and one by Penn. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 866 Stethoscope, wooden, replica of the Laennec style of stethoscope. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 867 Retractor, ca 1900, manufactured by M. Wocher. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 868 Gynecologic depressor, wooden handle, ca. 1890. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 869 Forceps, ca. 1900, perhaps lithotomy forceps, manufactured by Charriere, Paris. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 870 Throat mirror, stainless steel, 20th century. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 871 Tuning fork, ca. 1950, manufactured by Roerig. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 85 872 Ophthalmoscope with battery-powered light, ca. 1920., manufactured by the Wellsworth-Dezeng Company. Contained in a black case. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 86 873 Glass beaker, hand blown, ca. 1850, used by John Berrien Lindsley. Added to inventory January 12, 1995. Donated by Margaret Lindsley Warden.
- Box 86 874 Doctor's bag, brown leather, ca. 1890. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 86 875 Doctor's bag, black leather, ca 1890. Contains an assortment of obstetrical instruments. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 5 876 Scarificator, brass, twelve bladed ca. 1850. Has an eagle and shield symbol on the bottom. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 5 877 Scarificator, brass, nine bladed ca. 1850. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 5 878 Spring lancet, ca. 1840 manufactured by Zeitz, New York. Contained in a brown case with a gold eagle and shield symbol on the top. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 5 879 Cupping set cups with miscellaneous accessories ca. 1890, manufactured by Huston Brothers, Chicago. Contained in a black box. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 880 Amputating knife, long, ca. 1875, manufactured by Tiemann and Co. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Flexner Collection Box 1 881 Paper weight, bronze. Commissioned at the retirement of Dr. Simon Flexner from the Rockefeller Institute. Profile of Simon Flexner on the obverse and the front gate of the Rockefeller Institute on the reverse. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 882 Urethral syringe, hard rubber, ca. 1890, found in Nashville. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 883 Post-nasal balloon catheter for the control of bleeding in the nasopharynx, ca. 1950. Designed by Dr. Cyril Fox and manufactured by the Bittner Corporation. Contained in original cardboard box with a sheet of description and directions. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 884 Hypodermic "special" needle, manufactured by Becton Dickinson and Company. Contained in a purple top cardboard box. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 885 Hemometer, ca. 1890, manufactured by E. Leitz, Berlin, Germany. Contained in black case, incomplete and in poor condition. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 886 Surgical case, black leather ca. 1890 containing miscellaneous surgical instruments including clamps amputation saw, sutures, hypodermic needles, and tourniquet. The case was manufactured for the Theo Tafel Company, Nashville, but the instruments appear not to be original to the case Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 887 Amputation saw, ca. 1890, rusty. Added to inventory January, 1995.
- Box 8 888 Ashtray, brass, made from a spent, large gun shell ca. 1944. Slotted to hold cigarettes and a stand to hold matches. Made for Dr. Rosenfeld by a grateful patient, well used. Added to inventory January, 1995. Donated by Dr. Louis Rosenfeld.
- Box 63 889 Brooks, Barney. Letter from Dr. William S. Halsted in Baltimore, Md. to Dr. Barney Brooks. Dated February 11, 1914. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 72 890 Thermometer, vest pocket, worn by R. H. Kampmeier while in practice in Castle Gate Utah. Glass, contained in a twist fashioned aluminum carrying case. Added to inventory February, 1995. Donated by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier.
- Box 72 891 Patent Medicine. "Raspberry Leaves Rubus Strigosus, S. W. Gould & Bros. Botanic Garden Malden Mass." Contained in a sealed and unopened paper-wrapped box, ca. 1910. Added to inventory February, 1995. Donated by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier, [September 1985?].
- Box 72 892 Chloroform bottle, corked, amber, empty, manufactured for E. R. Squibb and Sons, ca. 1905. Added to inventory February, 1995. Donated by Dr. Rudolph H. Kampmeier, [September 1985?]
- Box 72 893 Medicine. Permian crystals, manufactured by Tarrant and Co. New York, contained in corked bottle, ca 1870. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 72 894 "Corn Plasters." manufactured by Bauer & Black, Chicago. Contained in a small black cardboard box, ca. 1898. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 72 895 Vaccine. "Glycerinized Vaccine Lymph on Ivory Points," manufactured by the National Vaccine Est., Washington. Contained in a light blue cardboard box, ivory point contained in a paraffine pocket, ca. 1898. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 72 896 Patent medicine. "Antikamnia & Quinine Laxative Tablets" manufactured by the Antikamnia Chemical Co., St. Louis." Contained in a sample tin tablet box, ca. 1890. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 72 897 Hypodermic tablet samples manufactured by Parke, Davis & Co., Detroit, Michigan. Atropine sulphate tablets contained in a sample tin box, ca. 1890. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 72 898 Patent medicine. "Sharp and Dohme Emulsion Petroleum Compound," large empty bottle ca 1910. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 32 899 Figurine, "Portrait of an Asthmatic Attack, Nayarit, Mexico, 400-800 A.D. " Primitive reproduction, carved from volcanic stone, (once upon a time) mounted on a wooden block, contained in a plastic bag. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 32 900 Wheat seed. Pyrex tube containing " First prize dark hard winter wheat Sterling Co., Variety -- Wichita, test weight 64.8, L. F. Givens." Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 7 901 Ophthalmoscope, battery-powered, ca. 1915, manufactured by the Welch Allyn, Co., Auburn, New York. Contained with attachments in a black case. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 7 902 Pocket case containing scalpels, clamps, depressors, forceps, etc. Case manufactured for the Theo Tafel Company, tri-fold black leather, ca. 1890, poor condition. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 7 903 Catheter, metal urethral, ca. 1890. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 7 904 Sound, conical, curved, used in the treatment of strictures. The numbers 25 and 14 are stamped on the handle, manufactured by Enqua -- Paris, ca 1890. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 7 905 Blood pressure apparatus patented and manufactured by G. P. Piling & Son Co., Philadelphia, ca. 1910. Contained in a black leather case, apparently incomplete. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 89 906 Battery box, portable, manufactured by V. Mueller & Company, ca. 1910, walnut with handle on top lid. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 7 907 Ophthalmic instruments, including ivory-handled scalpels, knives, retractors, forceps, hooks, etc. Contained in a black leather case manufactured for the Merowitz Bros., New York, ca. 1910. Most, but not all the instruments are manufactured by Merowitz. Belonged to a G. W. Hale, whose name is lettered on the top. Added to inventory February, 1995.
- Box 91 908 Nutritional food charts. Bar graphs on poster board showing values of particular foods in relation to various bodily functions. Also, there are a few thermofax transparencies. Note: that only the box is numbered and not the individual items. Added to inventory March, 1995. Donated by Bertlyn Bosley, 1990.
- Box 92 909 Plaques, certificates, and diplomas awarded to Bertlyn Bosley, Ph.D.; a silver plate inscribed "The Bertlyn Bosley Award of Excellence.. in North Carolina, 1981; and several Spanish language posters for nutritional awareness campaigns; box of starched collars and a black and white uniform cap (for dietitians?) Note: that only the box is numbered and not the individual items. Added to inventory in 1995. Donated by Bertlyn Bosley.
- Box 93 910 Carrying case, brown leather with alligator stamped pattern, purple felt interior containing medical instruments manufactured by Cameron's Surgical Specialty Co., ca. 1925. Observation instruments which are battery powered include: ophthalmoscope, speculum, endoscope, and a "Vitrohm Adjuster." Also, there are other attachments including bulbs and fuses. See also: boxes 45-48. Donated by Martin A. Meacham.
- Box 94 911 Miscellaneous dental instruments, ca. 1890-1920, belonging to Dr. John Benjamin Hopkins and Edna Love Hopkins. Instruments include: forceps, root extractors, and lancets. Note: that only the box is numbered and not the instruments contained within. Added to inventory March, 1995. Donated by Mrs. Ben Hopkins, July, 1989.
- Box 95A-B 911 Miscellaneous ophthalmologic and otolaryngological instruments and charts, ca. 1950- 1960, which belonged to William W. Wilkerson, M.D. Instruments include: head mirror, otoscope-ophthalmoscope, and retinoscope. Also, diagnostic plastic test objects, a three-dimensional vectographic exercise booklet, and an eye chart contained in a booklet. Note: that only the box is labeled. Added to inventory March 8, 1995.
- Box 96 912 Miscellaneous obstetrical and surgical instruments, ca. 20th century, including clamps, depressors, speculums, probes, retractors, forceps, hooks, curettes, douche, etc. Note: that only the box is labeled. Added to inventory March 8, 1994.
- Box 4 913 Vaccines. Three wooden tubes containing glycerinized vaccine lymph. Two are manufactured by H. K Mulford Co. and one by Parke Davis & Co. All three were manufactured for use by January, 1903. Contained in a short mailing tube. Added to inventory March, 1995.
- Box 4 914 Microscopic lenses (fourteen) of varying powers, ca. 1900 contained in a green leather covered case. Added to inventory March 8, 1995.
- Box 4 915 Scales, portable, golden colored, tripod with singular dish, (plastic -- not original) balanced above a curved, graduated scale which is attached to a counterweight. Ca. 1920, manufactured by Depose(?), Germany. Added to inventory March 9, 1995.
- Box 4 916 Magnifier used by travelling bible salesmen in the late nineteenth century. Squared metal rod with a graduated scale etched on the side, a stationary magnifying lens with a handle on one end, and a round metal plate with a handle which slides on the rod. The plate is inscribed with "count the dots" on the side of facing the lens. Appears to be ophthalmologic in nature. Added to inventory March 9, 1995.
- Box 4 917 Hydrometer, ca. 1920, double bulbed. The first is flat, and pill-shaped containing mercury. The second bulb is a larger and capsule-shaped. The flat section of the tube above the two bulbs has a graduated scale on a white insert. "Diabetes" and "Made in Germany" is printed on the opposite side of the insert. Contained in a black cardboard tube. Added to inventory March 9, 1995.
- Box 4 918 Trepanning elevator and rasps. Solid metal double-sided tool manufactured by J Reinders & Co., New York, ca 1880. Added to inventory March 10, 1995.
- Box 4 919 Two trepanning instruments ca. 18th and early 19th century. Lenticular knife, and a raspatory. Wooden handles and apparently part of a set. Added to inventory March 10, 1995
- Box 7 920 Pocket case for ampoules, ca. 1920. nickel silver, manufactured for Admiral B-D, Rutherford, New Jersey. Added to inventory March 10, 1995.
- Box 7 921 Aspirator, ca. 1900, includes rubber hoses and stoppers, and needles. Contained in a white cotton canvass roll-up case. Added to inventory March 10, 1995.
- Box 7 922 Cysto-lithic staff, channeled, stainless steel, ca 1900. Handle missing. Added to inventory March 10, 1995.
- Shelf 8 973 Mendeléff Dimitri Ivanovitsch. Framed portrait with biographical description of Dimitri Ivanovitsch Mendléff (1834-1907). Donated by Dr. E. Neige Todhunter (from the Department of Biochemistry), May 7, 1979. Added to inventory May 26, 1995. Transferred from Vanderbilt Department of Biochemistry.
- Box 24 1159 Booklet of WWII era German patient casulty tags used by doctors in the field to describe the extent of patient’s injuries, history etc. Donated by Dr. Henry M. Carney, September 6, 1995.